Guide to the Ruth Robinson Carroll Papers, 1913-1962
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Ruth Robinson Carroll Papers
1913-1962
Carroll, Ruth, 1899-
1.2 cubic feet (2 boxes, 1 OV folder)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Memory book of Ruth Robinson, 1913-1918; drawings, sketches, and manuscript drafts of Ruth and Latrobe Carroll's children's books, 1934-1962, including Bounce and the Bunnies, Scuffles, Old Mrs. Billups and the Black Cats, Where's the Bunny?, and Where's the Kitty?; and drafts and published versions of the article "Through the World of Silence," 1950.
Biographical Note
Ruth Robinson, writer, artist, and illustrator of children's books, was born in Lancaster, NY in 1899, where she formed an early interest in art. She majored in Art at Vassar and after graduation in 1922 continued her studies at the Art Students League and with private instructors. In 1928, she married Latrobe Carroll, an editor. Dissatisfied with sales of her paintings, she decided to turn her talents to illustrating animal stories for children. Sharing their Greenwich Village apartment with a series of models such as Puddles, a rabbit, Ruth Robinson Carroll published such children's books as Bounce the Bunnies and Chimp and Chump.
In 1934, Mr. Carroll quit his editorial work and began collaboration with his wife. The Carrolls were attracted to the landscape and people of Appalachia and in 1950 moved to North Carolina. Rural life in the Great Smokies region inspired a series of books about a mountain family, the Tatums, and their animals. In 1964 From the Appalachians, a portfolio of paintings and drawings by Mrs. Carroll, was published with an introduction by her husband. The Carrolls collaborated on a number of books, including Luck of Roll and Go, Scruffles, Tough Enough, Runaway Pony, and The Picnic Bear.
Scope and Content Note
Memory book of Ruth Robinson, 1913-1918; drawings, sketches, and manuscript drafts of Ruth and Latrobe Carroll's children's books, 1934-1962, including Bounce and the Bunnies, Scuffles, Old Mrs. Billups and the Black Cats, Where's the Bunny?, and Where's the Kitty?; and drafts and published versions of the article "Through the World of Silence," 1950.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Subject Headings
Names:
Carroll, Latrobe; Robinson, Ruth, 1899-
Subjects:
Children's literature--Women authors; Illustrated books, Children's; Women authors, American; Illustrators
Document Types:
Drawings (visual works)
VCL Categories:
Art and Artists; Children and Children's Literature; Literature and Writing
Encoding Information
Encoded by Elizabeth Clarke, November 2006. Updated by Emma Gronbeck, June 2024.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Ruth Robinson Carroll.
Series List
- Series I. Bounce and the Bunnies, New York: Harcourt, 1934
- Series II. Scruffles, London: Oxford University Press, 1943
- Series III. Old Mrs. Billups and the Black Cats, NY: Henry Z. Walck, 1961
- Series IV. Where's the Bunny?, NY: Oxford University Press, 1950
- Series V. Where's the Kitty?, NY: Henry Z. Walck, [1962]
- Series VI. Miscellaneous
Container List
- Bounce and the Bunnies, New York: Harcourt, 1934
  - Original drawings and color separation tracings, undated (Box 1, Folders 1-5)
- Scruffles, London: Oxford University Press, 1943
  - Dummy, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Old Mrs. Billups and the Black Cats, NY: Henry Z. Walck, 1961
  - Drafts 1-2, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Draft 3, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Draft 4, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Draft 5, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Draft 6, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Draft 7, with criticism by Latrobe "Toby" Carroll, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Manuscript sent to publisher, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Dummy, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Preliminary sketches, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Discarded sketches, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Drawings, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Gathering, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Where's the Bunny?, NY: Oxford University Press, 1950
  - Drafts, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Discarded sketches, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Dummy, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Illustrations, undated (Box 1, Folders 22-25)
  - Illustrations, undated (Box 1, Folders 26-27)
- Where's the Kitty?, NY: Henry Z. Walck, [1962]
  - Discarded sketches, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Sketches for final finished drawing, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Final drawings [?], undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Dummy, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Proof sheet, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Miscellaneous
  - Drafts of article "Through the World of Silence,", undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - "Through the World of Silence", The Horn Book, 1950 Sep-Oct (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Watercolor by Carroll of Vassar College Students Building, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - "Memory Book" of Ruth Robinson, 1913-1918 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Miscellaneous printed material, 1953-1962 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Autographed broadside of Runaway Pony, Runaway Dog, by Ruth & Latrobe Carroll, undated (Oversize Multi-Collection Box)